hi everyone my name is Antonin and I
will present today how to control two
three-phase brushless motors using one
f28 269 Launchpad there is a
prerequisite to better understand this
example I strongly recommend you watch
the video entitled simile motor control
with TI launchpad this previous video is
controlling one motor with an f28 2 to 7
launchpad I strongly recommend you go
through this video as it will explain
how to install the support packages
needed for this particular example so
here is the list of hardware required
for this demo you need an F 2806 9
Launchpad you need to boost Excel DRV
8301 booster packs
note that the f28 o-69 Launchpad can
take two booster packs at the same time
and these are the inverters so we're
gonna use one for each motor and you
need of course to PMS M three-phase
motors there is a packaged mini Dino kit
that you can get from Ti this is the
product code to MTR - Dino or you can
use any two PMS M motors that may be
shipping with other kids so here is what
I have on my table this is my F 2806 9
launch pad you can see the two slots for
the two booster packs this is my first
booster pack which is connected here to
this motor there are a lot of cables
here these are my QEP and Hall sensor
cables they are not connected today
because running sense or less the hole
sensors and QEP cable for the second
motor and you can see that the second
motor is connected to the second booster
pack so I'm going to connect both of
them to the f28 o-69 launchpad
there is no dumb proof connector so make
sure that you connect them correctly I
have a power supply here it's just a
laptop power supply that's not connected
right now that's gonna give me 20 volts
and I have shared that power supplied
across the two booster packs I also have
my 5 volt USB cable that I can connect
to my computer which will power the f28
or 6:9 launchpad and installation
functions that are good to remember
targets installer to install new support
packages target the Baader to make sure
that the third-party tools are correctly
installed and checky and be set up and
in this case it's good to run it against
CCS b5 or v6 f28 o-69 check that's
probably the configuration that will be
useful today so let me go to the Similan
model so here is what I use to control
the two motor so I'm just gonna generate
code and run it and then I will go
through explanations on how I got there
so I can press that Bell button it will
generate code for this model it will
invoke the CCS compiler and it will load
the code on the f28 o-69 launchpad that
I have connected right now to my USB
cable
I haven't connected high power yet let's
wait until we load the code then we'll
we can start the 20 volt to spin the
motors you can click on the view
diagnostic to follow the build steps you
can see the generated code being
compiled here we call a scripting tool
provided by CCS to load the code onto
the target my debug session is starting
I'm connecting to my target and my code
is loaded on my target it's a little
hard to see but I have an LED blinking
yeah you can see it here it's a blue LED
blinking just to see that the code is
running properly alright so the code is
flashed on the target so what I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna this
connect my USB cable so now nothing's
powered I'm going to connect my high
voltage I mean high voltage it's only 20
volts but this should spin the motors
now it should boot the code and provide
high power at the same time and now you
can see that both motors are spinning on
my dyno you can notice I haven't
connected the two motors together
they're just freely spinning right now
for the sake of the example of course
one thing you can do in the future is
connect these two and have one drive the
other and have one motor act as a load
while the other would be the motor on
the test so how did I get there so here
is my civic model one thing very
important always enable colors in your
model and if you look at the sample time
legend we have multiple colors here we
have this red red group which is running
at 50 micro we have one interrupt which
is asynchronous and I can tell you it's
running also at 50 micro so I'm running
these two motors at a twenty kilohertz
right I have a speed control loop every
10 milli so every 10 million I'm gonna
refresh my torque demand to both of
these torque control loops for each
motor and I have my LED blink at 0.5 so
I'm toggling the LED every 0.5 which
gives me a blinking period of one sec so
there are a few modeling concepts that I
would like to show with this demo so the
first one is the target selection make
sure you've selected the right target
the f28 o-69 launchpad comes with an F
2806 9 m and the M is very important in
that case it doesn't have the same
memory map as the other f28 to 69 so you
need to select the C 2806 9 m dot CMD
file it's not the same linker command
file as the regular f28 or 69 the
devices are similar but the IQ math
tables are located at a different memory
location for the
device so it's very important that you
select that M device which is provided
out of the box just press the Browse
button and you have all of them provided
here the plano 69 the 689 F and the 69 m
second modeling concept that I would
like to demonstrate is the PWM
synchronization so I have two motors and
the first motor is going to be
controlled by this side of the model
while the second motor is going to be
controlled by this side of the model the
two pwms have to be synchronized what I
do for that is I'm using PWM one two
three four the first motor and they're
triggering ad C a0 and b0 which are
sensing my eye a and IB for the first
motor I am using PWM four five six for
the second motor and they're triggering
ADC a3 and b3 so now like I demonstrated
before the PWM s are synchronized so the
first 3 1 2 & 3 are synchronized
together and the counters are just in
sync with each other the way I ensure
this is by sending the synchronization
pulse between PWM 1 2 & 3 the way you do
this is you set here synchronization
output and I'm gonna send the pulse when
the counter equals zero okay so this
will send the pulse to PWM 2 now you can
see on this first one I'm not reacting
on any pulse synchronization action is
disabled this is the initiator of the
pulse so it's my reference for the
synchronization now if I go to PWM 2
when counter of PWM 1 equals zero it
will send the synchronization pulse PWM
2 reacts on it by setting its own
counter to zero in that respect both of
them are synchronized they're all going
to be set to zero at the same time PWM 2
also outputs a synchronization pulse to
PWM 3 and in that case it's just a
pass-through
we don't want to do anything PWM one is
eventually going to reach PWM 3 via PWM
to with a pass through here on PWM 3
same as PWM - I'm gonna react on the
synchronization pulse by setting a
counter phase value to zero or one thing
I forgot to mention once you set this to
zero it has to count up after sync
because it's a counting mode is up and
down so when you reach zero obviously
after that you want to count up this is
important this also has to be set on PWM
- now what PWM is 3 does in the previous
video with the f28 o27 launchpad it was
just disabling the output because
nothing was there after that now I have
a second motor to synchronize so here I
am passing the synchronization output
pulse and this will reach PWM 4 so now
let's look at what we do with PWM for
PWM 4 is for the second motor and now
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
synchronize the counter of PWM 4 to the
counter period instead of synchronizing
it to 0 and 1 PWM 1 2 3 are reaching
zero PWM 4 is reaching the counter
period and you will see that I'm going
to do the same with 5 & 6 so 4 5 6 are
going to be set to the period while 1 2
3 are going to be set to 0 so in that
respect there defaced by 180 degrees
same deal I'm passing the
synchronization output pulse as a
pass-through so that will reach PWM 5
and PWM 5 is going to be the same as PWM
for setting the periods when you reach
the pulse and you can notice here the
countdown after sync when we reach the
period we want to count down and the
same I'm passing the synchronization
output PWM 6 is going to be the same
with the little difference that there is
nobody after that
the synchronization output reaches
finally a dead end and it's now disabled
so here is a picture that summarizes
what's happening in this model we have
our PWM sync triggering when the PWM one
counter reaches zero and that
synchronizes the counters of PWM 1 2 & 3
the PWM sync will also synchronize PWM 4
5 6
when PWM 1 is 0 PWM 4 5 6 will be set to
the counter period and we'll count down
after the synchronization you can see
the ADC triggers happening on the
periods of PWM 1 2 3 as well as the
periods of PWM 4 5 6 the ADC trigger of
PWM 1 2 3 will trigger ADC a 0 B 0 at
the end of the ADC conversion an
interrupt is generated and that will
trigger the field oriented control
algorithm for motor one when PWM 4 5 6
reaches the periods ADC trigger number 2
is happening and this will trigger ADC
a3 and b3 at the end of the conversion
an interrupt is generated and that will
trigger the field oriented control
algorithm for motor number 2 you can
notice that full PWM periods is set to
20 kilohertz or 50 microseconds so that
gives us about 25 microsecond maximum
for the ADC conversion and the field or
ant control algorithm for each motor so
you can notice that our code is running
pretty efficiently as it has to complete
within that 25 microsecond and leave
enough time for the lowest priority
tasks to execute the last modeling
concept I wanted to talk about is the
ability to trigger the Similan scheduler
based on an ADC interrupt if I go back
to my model you may have noticed that I
only have one interrupt that's
triggering the FOC algorithm for motor
number 2 I could create the same model
with two interrupts one for motor one
one for motor - the problem when we use
interrupts is you get that purple color
and similar ink loses the ability to
know that this is a pair
Eric interrupts which is associated with
a fixed sample time we can fix it for at
least one interrupt if I go to my config
set I have the ability to tell Simulink
to trigger the scheduler based on the
ADC interrupts instead of the standard
timer 0 by default the scheduler
interrupts source is set to timer 0 when
we do this we book CPU timer 0 we set
the periodicity of timer 0 to the base
rate of the Simulink model and that
triggers an interrupt at fixed interval
that's the red color in my model here I
have the ability to say I have set my
ADC interrupt to a specific rate
now please similarly use that interrupt
to schedule the entire scheduler instead
of timer 0 and that's what we do here
that offers the ability to keep a known
sample time and use blocks that would
need that sample time I'm thinking of
blocks like the buffer block like PID
blocks or any block that would need an
input sample time I hope this gives you
a good base to start playing with this
dual motor control setup for the future
as enhancements or things you can try
you can try to implement the sensor
based motor control algorithm using
either halls or QEP to do this you can
type on your MATLAB prompt there is a
standard demo if you type C 2806 9:00
p.m. sm FOC that will help you implement
the hall sensor based position sensing
there are other shipping demos like the
C 2808
PMS M FOC this one will show you how to
use a QEP to get the position of the
motor
there are also demos that will show you
how to use the CLA so we can put the FOC
algorithm on the CLA and therefore save
a lot of CPU time to do some lower
priority tasks the CLA would require a
conversion
the algorithm to the floating point
there is a shipping demo that will show
you how to use the CLA if you type C
2806 9 just tab it and you have C 2806
9p MSM FOC CLA that will show you how to
use the CLA and this CLA demo is also
using Hall sensors as a position
technique you could also do parameter
tuning and data logging via external
mode there is a canned connector on the
f28 o-69 launchpad you can go through
our external mode based on can demos to
start logging data and tune parameters
like PID gains while the motors are
spinning you can type C 28 X underscore
CCP and that is a good starting point
for external mode based on can another
good Avenue to pursue would be to
connect the two motors physically
together and start having one acting as
a load while you actively test the the
first motor I hope this helps and I hope
this gives you a lot of ideas to try
thanks for watching